{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "4.7","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["2", "3", "6", "8"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "6","explanation": "One unit of RBCs will raise the hemoglobin level by approximately 1.0 to 1.5 g/dL, and the hematocrit by 3% to 4%. Results vary, depending on the age of the blood and the patient’s blood volume and hydration status. Six units will raise the hemoglobin level to at least 12 g/dL."},"question": "A male patient with cancer was admitted to the hospital with acute abdominal pain and a hemoglobin level of 6 g/dL. Small bowel resection was indicated, but the attending physician wanted to raise the patient’s hemoglobin level to 12 g/dL before surgery. How many units of RBCs would most likely be required to accomplish this?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Blood components/RBCs/2"},{"choices": ["Prestorage filtration","Bedside filtration","Poststorage filtration","Buffy coat removal"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Buffy coat removal","explanation": "Removal of the buffy coat, which contains both platelets and white blood cells (WBCs), is not an approved method for leukocyte reduction of RBCs. The other methods can be employed to achieve a leukocyte reduction of less than 5 × 106."},"question": "Which of the following is not a viable method for removing leukocytes from RBCs?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Blood components/RBCs/1"},{"choices": ["The only problem is with the returned unit; the 30-minute limit has expired and the unit cannot be used","The unit should not have been transfused at 10:40 a.m. because the time limit had expired; this unit and the remaining unit should have been returned to the blood bank","The returned unit may be held for this patient for 48 hours but cannot be used for another patient","No problems; all actions were performed within the allowable time limits"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The only problem is with the returned unit; the 30-minute limit has expired and the unit cannot be used","explanation": "There is a 30-minute time limit for a unit of RBCs that is not kept under proper storage conditions (1°C–6°C)."},"question": "Four units of packed RBCs were brought to the nurses’ station at 10:20 a.m. Two units were transfused immediately, and 1 unit was transfused at 10:40 a.m. The remaining unit was returned to the blood bank at 11:00 a.m. The units were not refrigerated after leaving the blood bank. What problem(s) is (are) present in this situation?","reference": "Blood bank/Select course of action/Blood components/RBCs/3"},{"choices": ["4:00 p.m.", "6:00 p.m.", "7:00 p.m.", "8:00 p.m."],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "6:00 p.m.","explanation": "Platelet preparation from whole blood must be done within 8 hours of collection."},"question": "A unit of whole blood is collected at 10:00 a.m. and stored at 20°C to 24°C. What is the last hour at which platelet concentrates may be made from this unit?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/3"},{"choices": ["Rejuvenated RBCs may be made within 3 days of outdate and transfused or frozen within 24 hours of rejuvenation","Frozen RBCs must be prepared within 30 minutes of collection and may be used within 10 years","Irradiated RBCs must be treated within 8 hours of collection and transfused within 6 hours","Leukocyte-reduced RBCs must be prepared within 6 hours of collection and transfused within 6 hours of preparation"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Rejuvenated RBCs may be made within 3 days of outdate and transfused or frozen within 24 hours of rejuvenation","explanation": "Rejuvenated RBCs may be prepared within 3 days of the outdate of the unit and washed and transfused or frozen within 24 hours. A unit of RBCs may be frozen within 6 days of collection. An RBC unit can be irradiated any time prior to the expiration date; once irradiated, the unit must be transfused within 28 days of irradiation or the original outdate, whichever comes first. Leukocyte-reduced RBCs should be prepared within 6 hours of collection, but must be given within 24 hours, if prepared using an open system. Leukocyte-reduced RBCs prepared using a closed system may be kept until the original date of expiration."},"question": "Which of the following is acceptable according to the AABB standards?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of laboratory operations/Blood components/RBCs/2"},{"choices": ["The minimum platelet count must be 3.0 × 1011, pH must be 6.0 or greater","The minimum platelet count must be 3.0 × 1010, pH must be 6.2 or less","The minimum platelet count must be 3.0 × 1011, pH must be 6.2 or greater","The minimum platelet count must be 5.5 × 1010, pH must be 6.0 or less"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The minimum platelet count must be 3.0 × 1011, pH must be 6.2 or greater","explanation": "Single-donor platelets prepared by apheresis must contain a minimum of 3.0 × 1011 platelets, and pH must be 6.2 or higher throughout the shelf life of the product."},"question": "Which of the following is true regarding apheresis platelets?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of laboratory operations/Blood components/Platelets/1"},{"choices": ["Fresh frozen plasma (FFP)","Granulocytes","Cryoprecipitate","RBCs"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Granulocytes","explanation": "Patients with CGD cannot fight bacterial infections because of dysfunctional phagocytic enzymes; granulocyte concentrates are the product of choice for these patients."},"question": "What is the component of choice for a patient with chronic granulomatous disease (CGD)?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of laboratory operations/Blood components/3"},{"choices": ["pH","Glucose","Pan-genera detection (PGD) assay","Gram stain"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Pan-genera detection (PGD) assay","explanation": "The FDA has mandated that pH and glucose can no longer be used as a screening test for platelets. The Verax PGD assay has been FDA approved for both single-donor platelets and random-donor platelets for bacteria screening."},"question": "What method can be employed to detect bacteria in random donor platelets?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of laboratory operations/Blood components/Preparation of components/1"},{"choices": ["FFP must be prepared within 24 hours of collection","After thawing, FFP must be transfused within 24 hours","Storage temperature for FFP with a 1-year shelf life is –18°C or less","When thawed, FFP must be stored between 1°C to 6°C"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "FFP must be prepared within 24 hours of collection","explanation": "FFP must be prepared within 8 hours after collection or according to FDA-cleared operator manual/inserts."},"question": "All of the following statements regarding FFP are true, except:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/RBCs/1"},{"choices": ["Irradiate to prevent graft-versus-host-disease (GVHD)","Wash with 0.9% saline","Warm to 37°C with a blood warmer","Transport so that temperature is maintained at 20°C to 24°C"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Warm to 37°C with a blood warmer","explanation": "A patient having cold agglutinins might have a reaction to a cold blood product. The product should be warmed to 37°C before transfusion."},"question": "What may be done to RBCs before transfusion to a patient with cold agglutinin disease to reduce the possibility of a transfusion reaction?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Hemotherapy/RBCs/2"},{"choices": ["Must be issued within 24 hours","Must be issued within 48 hours","Must be irradiated","Must retain the original expiration date"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Must be issued within 24 hours","explanation": "The other half unit must be issued within 24 hours, if an open system is used to split the unit."},"question": "A unit of packed RBCs is split using the open system. One of the half units is used. What may be done with the second half unit?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of laboratory operations/Blood components/RBCs/2"},{"choices": ["Issue the unit; the blood will be filtered","Issue the unit; note the presence of a clot on the release form","Filter the unit in the blood bank before issue","Do not issue the unit"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Do not issue the unit","explanation": "A unit having a noticeable clot should not be issued for transfusion to a patient. The clot may be an indication of contamination or bacterial growth."},"question": "What should be done if a noticeable clot is found in an RBC unit?","reference": "Blood bank/Select course of action/Hemotherapy/RBCs/2"},{"choices": ["von Willebrand disease","Hypofibrinogenemia","Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","Factor XIII deficiency"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","explanation": "Cryoprecipitate may be used to treat von Willebrand disease, hypofibrinogenemia, and factor XIII deficiency, but is not indicated in ITP. IVIG is the product of choice for ITP."},"question": "Cryoprecipitate may be used to treat all of the following, except:","reference": "Blood bank/Select best course of action/Hemotherapy/Cryo/3"},{"choices": ["Cytospin/irradiator","Water bath/centrifuge","Centrifuge/sterile connecting device","Cell washer/heat sealer"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Centrifuge/sterile connecting device","explanation": "In the event of an ABO-mismatched stem cell transplant, special attention must be paid to the choice of transfused blood products. Type A or AB platelets may be given to a transplant in which the donor is type A and the recipient is type O; once the stem cells engraft, platelets/plasma must be compatible with type A cells. If only type O single-donor platelets are available, the product can be spun down using a centrifuge and plasma can be removed. Then, a sterile connecting device can be used to aseptically transfer sterile isotonic saline to the platelet product, replacing the incompatible plasma."},"question": "SITUATION: A transplant patient may receive only type A or AB platelets. Only type O apheresis platelets are available. What devices may be used to deplete the incompatible plasma and replace with sterile saline?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/Platelets/2"},{"choices": ["Whole blood","Packed RBCs","Washed or deglycerolized RBCs","Granulocytes"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Washed or deglycerolized RBCs","explanation": "Patients with anti-IgA antibodies should not receive components containing plasma. Washed or deglycerolized RBCs can be issued."},"question": "What component(s) is (are) indicated for patients who have anti-IgA antibodies?","reference": "Blood bank/Select course of action/Hemotherapy/2"},{"choices": ["12 months from latest date of collection of product in pool","12 months from earliest date of collection of product in pool","4 hours","6 hours"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "12 months from earliest date of collection of product in pool","explanation": "Expiration of pooled cryoprecipitate must take into account that there may be units that makeup the pool with differing collection dates where the earliest date is used to determine the expiration date."},"question": "What is the expiration date for pooled cryoprecipitate (pooled before freezing)?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/FFP/1"},{"choices": ["RBCs are washed with 1 to 2 L of normal saline","Volume is 180 mL","Shelf life is extended","Leukocytes are removed"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Shelf life is extended","explanation": "Washed RBCs renders the system “open” and shortens the expiration time to 24 hours."},"question": "All of the following are true regarding washed RBCs, except:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/Processing/1"},{"choices": ["Room temperature, 20°C to 24°C","No other components may be stored with platelets","Platelets must be stored upright in separate containers","Platelets require constant agitation at 20°C to 24°C"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Platelets require constant agitation at 20°C to 24°C","explanation": "Platelets require constant agitation and are stored at temperatures between 20°C and 24°C. Cold-stored platelets (single donor [apheresis] platelets stored at 1-6°C for up to 3 days) may be used for actively bleeding patients, but are not approved for treating thrombocytopenia."},"question": "What is a special condition for the storage of platelets?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/Processing/1"},{"choices": ["Exchange transfusion","Bone marrow transplantation","Severe combined immunodeficiency syndrome (SCIDS)","Warm autoimmune hemolytic anemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Warm autoimmune hemolytic anemia","explanation": "WAIHA would not require irradiation unless the patient had an underlying immunosuppressive disorder."},"question": "Transfusion of an irradiated product is indicated in all of the following conditions except:","reference": "Blood bank/Select course of action/Hemotherapy/Irradiation/2"},{"choices": ["75%", "80%", "85%", "100%"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "85%","explanation": "An RBC unit that has been leukocyte reduced must retain 85% of original RBCs."},"question": "What percentage of RBCs must be retained in leukocyte-reduced RBCs?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/1"},{"choices": ["The product must contain a maximum of 1.0 × 1010 granulocytes","pH must be 6.0","The product must be crossmatched","The product must be irradiated"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The product must be crossmatched","explanation": "Granulocyte concentrates contain a large amount of RBCs (greater than 2 mL) that must be crossmatched with the recipient’s serum."},"question": "Which of the following is true regarding granulocyte concentrates?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/2"},{"choices": ["Issue the unit","Discard the unit","Change the expiration date; then issue the unit","Note on the irradiation sticker that the unit was irradiated twice, and then issue the unit"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Discard the unit","explanation": "If an MLS mistakenly irradiates a unit of RBCs more than once, the unit must be discarded because of subsequent potassium accumulation. This does not apply to platelets."},"question": "What course of action should be taken if an MLS inadvertently irradiates a unit of RBCs twice?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Irradiation/2"},{"choices": ["Frozen RBCs and cryoprecipitate","Platelets","Packed RBCs and granulocytes","Double RBC units"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Frozen RBCs and cryoprecipitate","explanation": "FFP requires dry ice for shipment. Frozen RBCs and cryoprecipitate also require dry ice."},"question": "What components(s) may be shipped together with FFP?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/FFP/1"},{"choices": ["Before 9:00 p.m.","Before 11:00 p.m.","Before 12:00 a.m.","Before 5:00 p.m. the next day"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Before 9:00 p.m.","explanation": "A thawed unit of pooled cryoprecipitate must be dispensed within 4 hours unless a sterile connecting device was used, which would extend expiration to 6 hours."},"question": "A blood supplier ships 3 units of pooled cryoprecipitate. Each pool consists of 5 units of cryoprecipitate. If one unit is thawed at 5:00 p.m., when must it be dispensed from the blood bank?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/FFP/1"},{"choices": ["Gamma rays and x-rays destroy the lymphocytes’ ability to divide","X-rays cause lysis of the lymphocytes","Gamma rays enhance lymphocyte reactivity","Ultraviolet radiation induces apoptosis of lymphocytes"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Gamma rays and x-rays destroy the lymphocytes’ ability to divide","explanation": "Gamma rays or x-rays have the ability to prohibit a lymphocyte’s ability to divide, preventing TA-GVHD."},"question": "How does irradiation prevent transfusion-associated graft-versus-host disease (TA- GVHD)?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/Stem cells/1"},{"choices": ["Cryoprecipitate","FFP","Frozen RBCs","Platelet concentrates"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Frozen RBCs","explanation": "Frozen RBCs may be kept for up to 10 years, or longer if the transfusion service or blood center has a policy for extension beyond 10 years. FFP and cryoprecipitate stored at –18°C or lower expire in 1 year. If FFP is kept at –65°C or lower, the expiration time is 7 years. Platelet concentrates expire from 24 hours to 5 days, depending on the collection system used."},"question": "Which component has the longest expiration date?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood bank/Expiration date/1"},{"choices": ["Less preparation time","Less antigen exposure for patients","May be HLA matched","No pooling is required"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Less preparation time","explanation": "Single-donor platelets require more preparation time compared with random-donor platelets because they are prepared by apheresis, which may require 1 to 3 hours, depending on the instrumentation used. Pooling random donor platelets in equivalent amounts may require only a few minutes."},"question": "All of the following are advantages of using single-donor platelets as opposed to random donor platelets, except:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Blood components/Platelets/1"},{"choices": ["4 hours", "6 hours", "8 hours", "24 hours"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "4 hours","explanation": "When individual cryoprecipitate units are pooled in an open system, the expiration time is 4 hours; if cryoprecipitate is pooled using a sterile connecting device, the expiration time is 6 hours."},"question": "What is the expiration of cryoprecipitate once pooled without the use of a sterile connecting device?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/Expiration date/1"},{"choices": ["Less than 5 × 1010","Less than 5 × 106","Less than 8.3 × 105","Less than 8.3 × 106"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Less than 5 × 106","explanation": "RBCs that have been leukocyte reduced must have fewer than 5 × 106 WBCs per unit."},"question": "What is the number of WBCs permitted in a unit of leukocyte-reduced RBCs?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Blood components/1"},{"choices": ["Liquid plasma and cryoprecipitate","Crossmatched platelets and washed RBCs","Factor IX concentrates and FFP","Irradiated RBCs, platelets, and granulocytes"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Irradiated RBCs, platelets, and granulocytes","explanation": "The patient with cancer may be immunocompromised because of the medication used but needs to receive RBCs for anemia; therefore, irradiated RBCs are indicated. Platelets may be needed to control bleeding, and granulocytes may be indicated for short-term control of severe infection."},"question": "SITUATION: A patient with cancer recently developed a severe infection. The patient’s hemoglobin level is 8 g/dL as a result of chemotherapy with a drug known to cause bone marrow depression and immunodeficiency. Which blood products are indicated for this patient?","reference": "Blood bank/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Blood and components/3"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Components"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}